<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Theologicall and scholasticall positions concerning vsurie Set forth by definitions; framed according to the rules of a naturall method.</title>
            <author>Powel, Gabriel, 1576-1611.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09891</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20155</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105149</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840879</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840879</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5421</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09891)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5421)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 933:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Theologicall and scholasticall positions concerning vsurie Set forth by definitions; framed according to the rules of a naturall method.</title>
                  <author>Powel, Gabriel, 1576-1611.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 71, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, and are to bee solde in Fleete-Streete [, London] at the signe of the Turkes head by Iohn Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Do. 1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Gabriel Powel.</note>
                  <note>A different work from his "Theologicall positions concerning the lawfulnesse of borrowing upon usurie".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Interest --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Usury --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5421:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5421:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THEOLOGICALL AND SCHOLAS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TICALL POSITI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS CONCER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Vſurie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Set forth by Definitions and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions; framed according to the Rules of a naturall Method.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by JOSEPH BARNES, and are to bee ſolde in Fleete-Streete at the ſigne of the Turkes head by JOHN BARNES. <hi>An. Do.</hi> 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5421:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5421:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp; most religious Gentlemen, <hi>RALPH HOCKENHVLL,</hi> &amp; <hi>HVGH HVRLESTON,</hi> Eſquires, all Grace &amp; Peace externall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, eternall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O write againſt <hi>Vſury</hi> (Right worſhipfull) is no noveltie; &amp; to giue the <hi>Vſurer</hi> notice of the daungers wherein he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, is a thing neceſſarily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in all Ages; begunne by our Fathers, who gaue the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:5421:3"/>on-ſet, ſeconded by Vs, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the skirmiſh, and to be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed of our Poſterities, whoe doubtleſſe will willingly followe their Fathers, wherein we haue ſo happily followed ours. The Sin is hainous, and the daunger deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; yea ſo much the more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is covert &amp; ſhrow ded; as a conſuming feaver, that cannot be eſpied before it growe incurable. I know there be many, otherwiſe good Chriſtians, that entertaine this vgly monſter, who would not doe it to gaine all the worlde, if they knewe their trade were <hi>damned-vſury.</hi> Giue me leaue therfore (Right worſhipful) to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipher the deceiptfullnes of this
<pb facs="tcp:5421:3"/>Sinne, by pointing at ſome vſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious practiſes, which are vtterlie vnlawful though commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly they be not ſo accompted. I wil touch but ſome fewe of the principall, leaſt I ſhoulde treade an endleſſe maze, &amp; enter a labirinth out of which Theſeus himſelfe were not able to reduce me.</p>
            <p>FIRST the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this covert &amp; ſhrow ded vſurie is committed in buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Selling.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>I buy barly afore hand for</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>a combe which at the time of the delivery (I know) will be worth</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>or a noble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is <hi>cloaked Vſurie.</hi> Becauſe that for payment before hande, I buy a great deale the cheaper.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>I ſell my wares: I giue a day of
<pb facs="tcp:5421:4"/>payment, and for that I am to forbeare my money ſo long, I ſell aboue mine ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary price, or aboue a reaſonable gaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein (no queſtion) I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <hi>vſury.</hi> Becauſe I ſell the time, and make a gaine of lending.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>A man comes to me to borrowe money: I anſwere, I will lend him no mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney for vſury. But if he vvil buy a horſe of me for</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">li</hi>. (<hi>which is ſcarce vvorth</hi> 20<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>.) <hi>I will lend him ſo much mony for ſuch a time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is <hi>vſurie.</hi> Becauſe the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny which ſurmounteth the price of the Horſe, is a ful recompence for the loane.</p>
            <p>SECONDLY, It is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of Letting.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>One comes to mee to borrow an</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:5421:4"/>100<hi rend="sup">li</hi> 
               <hi>for</hi> 7. <hi>yeeres. I anſwer, He ſhal haue it; if he will hire a houſe of me for</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">li</hi>. <hi>yeerely,</hi> (<hi>which is ſcarce worth</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>.) <hi>and take a leaſe of the ſame du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſaide tearme of</hi> 7. <hi>yeeres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is plaine <hi>Vſurie.</hi> Becauſe the rent of the houſe payeth for the loane of the money.</p>
            <p>THIRDLY, It is committed in Lending.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>I come to a man to borrow mony. He will lend me ſo much as I aske, but in light gould, in crackt angels, or ſuch like. Yet he vvill haue payment in good currant money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is <hi>Vſurie.</hi> Becauſe he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a manifeſt gaine of Lending</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>If in conſideration of a piece of money ſent I take a piece of ground, a
<pb facs="tcp:5421:5"/>houſe, or cattel, or any fructifieng thing, vntill the mony be paide againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is <hi>Vſurie.</hi> Vnleſſe that the fruite I reaped from the pledg be diducted from the principall.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>If for ſuch a conſideration, I take for pleadg apparell, plate. &amp;c. and vſe the ſame vntil paiment be made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is <hi>Vſurie.</hi> Becauſe I reap comodity by the vſe of the pledg for the Loane onelie.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>I deliver</hi> 20<hi rend="sup">li</hi> 
               <hi>vppon condition to haue</hi> 22<hi rend="sup">li</hi> 
               <hi>at the yeares end, if I be the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> living, but if I die to haue but</hi> 18<hi rend="sup">li</hi> 
               <hi>reſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is plaine <hi>Vſurie.</hi> 1 Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the gaine is certaine, in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the Lender, and that for the Lone onely. 2 Becauſe there
<pb facs="tcp:5421:5"/>is no reſpect had whether the bor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowers gaine be lawful or not, yea whether he gaine any thing at all or no. 3 Becauſe the Lender doth not adventure the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall. 4 Becauſe he doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vpon GODS providence for diſpoſing, and ordering of his Goodes: but is ſure of Gaine (if he liues,) howſoever it goeth with the Borrower.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>I deliver</hi> 20<hi rend="sup">li</hi>. <hi>vpon condition to haue</hi> 22<hi rend="sup">li</hi> 
               <hi>at the yeares ende, if either my ſelfe, or one other who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhal name, be then living, but if we be both deade at the ſame time, then no part of paiment at all to be made, neither of gaine nor of principall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is <hi>Vſurie:</hi> for the reaſons
<pb facs="tcp:5421:6"/>
               <hi>houſe, or cattel, or any fructifieng thing, vntill the mony be paide againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is <hi>Vſurie.</hi> Vnleſſe that the fruite I reaped from the pledg be diducted from the principall.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>If for ſuch a conſideration, I take for pleadg apparell, plate. &amp;c. and vſe the ſame vntil paiment be made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is <hi>Vſurie.</hi> Becauſe I reap comodity by the vſe of the pledg for the Loane onelie.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>I deliver</hi> 20<hi rend="sup">li</hi> 
               <hi>vppon condition to haue</hi> 22<hi rend="sup">li</hi> 
               <hi>at the yeares end, if I be the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> living, but if I die to haue but</hi> 18<hi rend="sup">li</hi> 
               <hi>reſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is plaine <hi>Vſurie.</hi> 1 Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the gaine is certaine, in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the Lender, and that for the Lone onely. 2 Becauſe there
<pb facs="tcp:5421:6"/>is no reſpect had whether the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers gaine be lawful or not, yea whether he gaine any thing at all or no. 3 Becauſe the Lender doth not adventure the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall. 4 Becauſe he doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vpon GODS providence for diſpoſing, and ordering of his Goodes: but is ſure of Gaine (if he liues,) howſoever it goeth with the Borrower.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>I deliver</hi> 20<hi rend="sup">li</hi>. <hi>vpon condition to haue</hi> 22<hi rend="sup">li</hi> 
               <hi>at the yeares ende, if either my ſelfe, or one other who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhal name, be then living, but if we be both deade at the ſame time, then no part of paiment at all to be made, neither of gaine nor of principall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is <hi>Vſurie:</hi> for the reaſons
<pb facs="tcp:5421:7"/>before alleadged.</p>
            <p>OBIECTION. <hi>I aduenture to looſe not onely the profit of my mony for a whole yeare, but alſo to looſe the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall it ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANSWER. No, no: Here is no aduenture at all. 1 For if the <hi>Vſurer</hi> liues his gaine is certaine howſoever the Borrower ſhal do 2 The aduenture muſt not onely be in reſpect of the Lender, but al ſo and that principally in reſpecte of the Borrower, whoe vſeth the money.</p>
            <p>FOVRTHLY It is committed in laying to pawne.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>I lend</hi> 20<hi rend="sup">li</hi> 
               <hi>for ayeare, and for aſsura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of mine ovvne, I take a pawne worth</hi> 30. <hi>or</hi> 40<hi rend="sup">li</hi> 
               <hi>vvith a bill of ſale,
<pb facs="tcp:5421:7"/>that in deſalte of payment at the day ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointed the pawne ſhall be my owne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is <hi>Vſurie:</hi> If either I hope the pawne ſhall be forfeited; or it I take the aduantage of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, if it ſo fal out.</p>
            <p>I am to bould to trouble your Worſhips with recital of particu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler Practiſes: yet, becauſe I know it is the cuſtome of many men ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſcan over Epiſtles &amp; prefa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diligently to peruſe whol books; I thought good to reſerue eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this place, for theſe few caſes that al Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>may ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> briefly cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, &amp; proved to be within com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſſe of <hi>manifeſt Vſurie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many learned Diuines haue written concerning this point. I
<pb facs="tcp:5421:8"/>haue read all that euer I coulde come by, <hi>Fathers, Canonistes,</hi> and <hi>moderne VVriters:</hi> &amp; made choice of what I iudged beſt out of them al, which I haue couched together conciſely, and methodically: ſo as the Reader may compendiouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly as it were with one proiect, take a view of the whole, what hath bin written concerning VSVRIE.</p>
            <p>This Labour (how greate or how ſmall ſoeuer) I humblie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto your Worſhips ioyntly, and ſeuerally, as a token of the dutiefull regard, and louing affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I beare vnto you: being not otherwiſe any way able to declar my thankfulnes, for the great and manyfolde favours &amp; benefites
<pb facs="tcp:5421:8"/>which from time to time I haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiued from you hartely beſeech<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing your VVorſhips, ſo to accept this ſmall gift, as it is conſecrated and dedicated vnto you; that is, with a willing, chearful, &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian minde.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>The</hi> LORD IESVS <hi>bleſse and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue your</hi> VVORSHIPS <hi>and perfect the good work he hath begun in you, that you may appeare blameleſse in the day of the</hi> LORD. </salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>OXON. From</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Marie Hall;</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 1. <hi>of Aprill, An. Do.</hi> 1602.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your VVorſhippes most hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie to commaund. <hi>GABRIEL POWEL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:5421:9"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 1.</label> Of the Kindes &amp; differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of <hi>Vſurie.</hi> Pag n.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 2:</label> Of the Defini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of <hi>Vſurie.</hi> 9.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 3:</label> Of the Difference betweene <hi>Vſury</hi> and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. 12:</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 4:</label> Whether it be lawful to lend for <hi>Vſury?</hi> 16:</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 5:</label> That <hi>Vſurie</hi> is vnlawfull &amp; damnable. 27:</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 6:</label> Howe great a Sinne <hi>Vſurie</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? 38</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 7:</label> Obiections for <hi>Vſurie</hi> anſwered: 42:</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 8:</label> Whether it be in a Mans own free choice to Lend or no? 55:</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 9:</label> Whether it be lawfull to borrow vpon <hi>Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie?</hi> 58.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 10:</label> What <hi>Vſurers</hi> ſhould do with their gain? 67</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5421:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> Of the kindes and Differences of Vſurie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His word <hi>VSVRIE,</hi> is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in divers ſenſes &amp; ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications: <hi>Properly,</hi> and <hi>Improperly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Properly,</hi> it ſignifieth <hi>the vſe of a thing,</hi> as is manifeſt by the Etymologie of the worde; for <hi>Vſurie</hi> is derived from <hi>vſing; Vſura, quaſi vſus rei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 The name of VSVRIE is not evill, but the abuſing of it, in applying it to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill trades and actions.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Improperly (Metonymicè, Cauſa pro Effecto)</hi> when we take it for <hi>the increaſe</hi> that ariſeth of it.</p>
            <p n="5">5 In this ſenſe <hi>Vſurie</hi> is two fold <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable</hi> and <hi>Vnprofitable.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:5421:10"/>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Profitable Vſurie,</hi> is a gaine or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe that ariſeth from the labour and exerciſe of our lawful callings.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Profitable vſurie is two fold, <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> or Terrene and Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall.</p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>Naturallor Terrene Vſurie,</hi> is that gaine which commeth and encreaſeth by tillage of the earth.</p>
            <p n="9">9 This vſurie is lawfull, becauſe it is the ordinance of God himſelfe; the anci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>enteſt trade, firſt practiſed in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 4.2.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>Spirituallor Celeſtiall vſury</hi> is that gaine and glory wherewith God rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the graces and good workes of his owne children.</p>
            <p n="11">11 And this is either, <hi>Privatiue,</hi> or <hi>Poſitiue,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Privative Spirituall vſury</hi> is when we forſake or reſuſe temporary commo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dities to gaine eternall.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:5421:10"/>
            <p n="13">13 Of this Chriſt ſpeaketh when hee ſaith <hi>Math</hi> 19 29. <hi>VVhoſoever ſhal for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or Mother, or wife, or children, or lands for my names ſake, hee ſhall receiue an hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dred fold more, and ſhall inherite everlaſting life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>Poſitiue ſpirituall vſurie</hi> is when we do any deed or acte for Gods glory, and the good of men, which ſhall bee crowned in heaven.</p>
            <p n="15">15 This poſitiue ſpiritual vſury is two fold, <hi>Giuing of Almes,</hi> and <hi>Imploying of Geds giftes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>Giuing of Almes</hi> is munificence and liberality towardes the poore and needie.</p>
            <p n="17">17 This is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended in the Scriptures. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.17. <hi>He lendeth to vſurie to the Lord that is mercifull to the poore.</hi> He is as it were the Lords vſurer; and ſhall be well rewarded.</p>
            <p n="18">18 And commaunded by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5421:11"/>
               <hi>Deuter.</hi> 15.10. <hi>Thou ſhalt giue him, and let it not greeue thine heart to giue vnto him. Math.</hi> 5.42. <hi>Giue to him that aſketh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>Imploring of Gods gifts</hi> is the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpoſing of thoſe graces that wee haue receaued from God, to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of his glorie and the benefite of Men.</p>
            <p n="20">Of this Chriſt ſpeaketh, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.27. <hi>Thou oughteſt to haue put forth my money to the exchaungers, and then at my comming ſhoulde I haue received my ovvne</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>vvith vſurie.</hi> See <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.23.</p>
            <div n="unprofitable usury" type="section">
               <head>Thus much of Profitable Vſurie. If followeth to ſpeake of that which is Vnprofitable.</head>
               <p n="21">21 <hi>Vnprofitable vſurie,</hi> is a Gaine or increaſe vnlawfully exacted or hoped,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5421:11"/>for the verie dutie of lending.</p>
               <p n="22">22 It is tearmed <hi>vnprofitable,</hi> becauſe in the ende it turneth into a curſe, and to bitternes to the Receiver or Vſurer.</p>
               <p n="23">23 Vnprofitable vſury is either <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall</hi>
or <hi>Politicall and Civill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="24">24 <hi>Eccleſiaſticall vſury</hi> is an increaſe vnlawfully exacted for nothing, vnder colour of preſcription or duty.</p>
               <p n="25">25 <hi>Civill or Politicall vſurie</hi> is when gaine and increaſe is raiſed from the vſe of worldly goods, which are thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the civill and politicke eſtats of Men.</p>
               <p n="26">26 Political vſurie is two-fold, <hi>Actuall</hi> and <hi>Mentall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="27">27 <hi>Actual vſury</hi> is committed, when one doth any act for gaine or increaſe.</p>
               <p n="28">And this is two-fold, <hi>Liberal,</hi> and <hi>by Compact</hi> or Covenant.</p>
               <p n="29">29 <hi>Liberall vſury</hi> is when he that bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth deſireth to make ſome recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:5421:12"/>
               <p n="30">30 That which is receiued aboue the principall is vſurie; yet this is not to bee condemned in three reſpects.</p>
               <p n="31">31 <hi>First</hi> Becauſe it is the duty of thankfulnes to make amends for a bene fit receiued.</p>
               <p n="32">32 <hi>Secondly</hi> becauſe it proceedeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the givers freewill Now what is more free then gift?</p>
               <p n="33">33 <hi>Thirdly Volenti non fit iniuria:</hi> If hee will giue it vnasked and vncompel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he hath no iniury offered in the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
               <p n="34">34 <hi>Vſury by compact</hi> or covenant is when the lender covenanteth with the Borrower to receiue againe not onely the principall, but alſo increaſe and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
               <p n="35">35 This vſury is two fold <hi>Manifeſt</hi> and <hi>Covert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="36">36 <hi>Manifeſt vſurie</hi> is when one doth covenant to take tenne (more or leſſe) in the hundred for a yeare &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:5421:12"/>
               <p n="37">37 Manifeſt vſurie is two fold <hi>Leſſe-Evill</hi> and <hi>More-Evill</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="38">38 <hi>Leſſe-Evil.</hi> is either of the <hi>Rich,</hi> or of <hi>Orphans and widdowes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="39">39 <hi>Of the Rich</hi> who giue money v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vſury vnto the Rich, to Marchants and Princes; though not vnto the Poore.</p>
               <p n="40">40 <hi>Of Orphans and widdowes,</hi> when their Overſeers, or Guardians doe put out money for their vſe.</p>
               <p n="41">41. <hi>More evill</hi> and murdering <hi>vſurie,</hi> is when the poore is bound to the rich to pay increaſe for the lone onely.</p>
               <p n="42">42 <hi>Covert or cloſe vſurie,</hi> is when one lendeth money, and ſhorowdeth it vnder ſome other bargaine.</p>
               <p n="43">43 As if I lend a man a 100<hi rend="sup">li</hi>. for a yeare, vppon condition that hee buy a horſe of mee (which peradventure is worth ſome 30.<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>.) and paye mee for it 10.<hi rend="sup">li</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="mental usury" type="section">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:5421:13"/>
               <head>So of Actual vſurie. Now of Mentall.</head>
               <p n="44">44 <hi>Mentall vſurie,</hi> is when one lendeth and doth not compact, but expecteth and hopeth for increaſe or gaine.</p>
               <p n="45">45 Sole hope maketh an Vſurer. If thou doeſt but expect to receiue more then thy owne, thou art an vſurer, ſaith Auguſtine. <hi>Aug. in Pſalm.</hi> 36. <hi>Ser.</hi> 33.</p>
               <p n="46">46 And CHRIST himſelfe ſaith <hi>Luc.</hi> 6.35. <hi>Lend, looking for nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>So much for the kindes and differences of vſurie. Now we will ſpeake one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of Civill Actuall vſurie, which is commonly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed amongſt vs.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:5421:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Of the Definition of Vſurie</head>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>VSVRIE is a gaine which by compoſition, compact, and agree<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment going before, is raken for the verie duetie of lending, not adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the principall; and that not onelie in money but in meate, ware, or any thing that is valuable by money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>Efficient cauſe</hi> of Vſurie is two fold, <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>leſſe principall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 The <hi>Principall and chiefeſt cauſe of vſurie</hi> is the DIVELL, who ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h vs vp to oppreſſion.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The <hi>leſſe principall, or ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate cauſes</hi> are covetouſnes, the loue of our ſelues, and the hatred of our neig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:5421:14"/>
            <p n="5">5 The <hi>Material Cauſe,</hi> is mony, come, cile, or ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The <hi>Formall Cauſe</hi> is the compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, compact, or agreement.</p>
            <p n="7">7 The <hi>Finall Cauſe</hi> is the enriching of our ſelues, by impoveriſhing of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Vſurie is <hi>a Gaine,</hi> becauſe it is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe aboue the principall, for the vſe and lending only.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Lending</hi> is a contract which tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth the dominion &amp; right of a thing to an other, with promiſe to haue the ſame thing deliuered againe, without price or conſiceration.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Lending is two-folde <hi>Mutuation</hi> and <hi>Accomodation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Mutuation</hi> is when a man lends any thing &amp; lookes but to haue his own againe in the ſame kinde.</p>
            <p n="12">12 As when I lend mony, I looke not to haue the ſame mony againe; but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of that kinde, in the ſame meaſure
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5421:14"/>and quantitie.</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>Accomodation</hi> is when a man lends ſome thing, and lookes to haue the ſame againe in his owne individuall proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p n="14">14 As if I lend a horſe, I looke to haue the ſame horſe againe, and not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="15">15 Vſurie is properly &amp; truely in that lending which is termed <hi>Mutuation</hi> &amp; in no other contract.</p>
            <p n="16">16 Vſurie is <hi>by Compact, compoſition, and agreement going before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>A Compact or Compoſition</hi> is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, <hi>Silent</hi> and <hi>Expreſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>A Silent Compact</hi> is when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Agreement is intended: As,</p>
            <p n="19">19 When a man comes to an vſu ei, to borrow money, hee tels him, <hi>that hee will allow him after</hi> 10. <hi>in the</hi> 100 al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the vſurer ſaith nothing; this is a kind of compact. Or,</p>
            <p n="20">20 If one comes to borrowe money,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5421:15"/>and the vſurer ſaith <hi>he wil take after</hi> 10. <hi>in the</hi> 100 albeit the borrower ſaith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but takes the money; it is a kinde of compact.</p>
            <p n="21">21 <hi>An expreſse compact</hi> is either <hi>Bare</hi> or <hi>Shrowded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22 <hi>Bare compact</hi> is when one comes to borrow mony, the Vſurer asketh him <hi>if he will giue vſe for it,</hi> the Borrower ſaith, <hi>he will.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>Shrowded co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pact</hi> is either <hi>in VVords</hi> or <hi>in writing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24 <hi>In words</hi> when the Borrower paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his promiſe for payment of vſe.</p>
            <p n="25">25 <hi>In writing</hi> when the Vſurer takes ſpecialty for the vſe of his money.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> The difference betweene Vſurie &amp; Intereſt.</head>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5421:15"/>
            <p n="1">1 THe Vſurers to gloſe with the worlde are wont to confound the names of <hi>intereſt</hi> and <hi>vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 But the difference between them is manifeſt by the deſinition of both of them</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Vſurie</hi> is defined before. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Poſit.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Intereſt is a debte vvhich one ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to another by the lawe of Nature and Aequitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>INTEREST is due</hi> two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of waies, <hi>By reaſon of Loſſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered;</hi> and <hi>By reaſon of Gaine hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>By reaſon of loſſe ſuffered:</hi> As when I borrowe money for another, and enter by bond for it, and take the like of him that receiveth the money, I may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully recover that I looſe by that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>By reaſon of Gaine hindered:</hi> As
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5421:16"/>if I being a Tradeſ-man lend my mony freely to my Neighbour till ſuch a day, hauing then occaſion to vſe it at ſome Faire, to lay it out in ware: if hee breake touch, I may lawfully take ſo much as I ſuſtained loſſe, for want of mony to lay out.</p>
            <p n="8">8 If a man ſuſtaine no loſſe or hurt, or can forbeare the mony ſo differred, if then hee take any thing for the forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, it is <hi>Vſurie</hi> and not <hi>Intereſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 For <hi>Intereſt</hi> is ſo called, becauſe one may ſay <hi>inter fuit mea habuiſse:</hi> It beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me, it ſtood me vpon to haue it, and now by your default ſuſtaine loſſe.</p>
            <p n="10">10 The difference betweene them is great, and eaſie to be diſcerned.</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Vſurie</hi> is an ouer plus or gaine ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more then was lent.</p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Intereſt</hi> is neither gaine nor ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus aboue the principall, but a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence demaunded and due for the loſſe that is ſuffered, or the gaine that is hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5421:16"/>through lending.</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>Vſurie</hi> groweth due by lending, from the day of borrowing vntill the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time of payment.</p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>Interest</hi> is neuer due but from the appointed day of payment forward, for ſo long as I forbeare my goods after the daie in which I did covenant to receaue them againe.</p>
            <p n="15">15 In <hi>vſurie</hi> I ſeeke to be a gainer.</p>
            <p n="16">16 In <hi>Intereſt</hi> ſeeke only to be no loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer; gaine or profit I ſeeke none.</p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>Vſurie</hi> is againſt all equity, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and reaſon.</p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>Intereſt</hi> ſtandeth with equity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and good reaſon.</p>
            <p n="19">19 <hi>Obiect.</hi> But here it wil be <hi>obiected.</hi> Why then doth Salomon conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt as well as Vſurie, for ſo hee ſaith, Prov. 28.8. <hi>He that increaſeth his riches by vſury and intereſt gathereth them for him that wil be mercifull vnto the poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5421:17"/>brewe hath it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Beneſhech vetarbith: by vſurie and increaſe</hi> or <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perabundance.</hi> So do all the Interpreters that I ſaw tranſlate it, ſauing our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</p>
            <p n="21">21 The <hi>Septuagint</hi> reade <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Vſurâ &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>perabundantiâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22 <hi>Tremelius, Leo Iuda, Lavaterus, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablus, Pagninus</hi> and <hi>Mercerus</hi> haue, <hi>Vſurâ &amp; foenore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>Arias Montanus. Vſurâ &amp; augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 4:</hi> VVhether it be lawfull to lend for Vſurie.</head>
            <p n="1">1 THat it is not lawfull to lende for vſury, appeareth as well <hi>by Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies</hi> as a ſo <hi>by Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 By <hi>Teſtimonies,</hi> Of the <hi>Law,</hi> of <hi>Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels,</hi> of <hi>Doctors,</hi> of <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> of <hi>Poets,</hi> and of <hi>the Conſtitutions of this Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:5421:17"/>
            <p n="3">3 The <hi>Law</hi> is foure-fold, The <hi>lawe of Nature,</hi> the <hi>law of God,</hi> the <hi>Civill &amp; the Canon law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>the law of Nature</hi> to lende vpon vſurie is vnlawful, becauſe it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, contrary vnto Nature: which thus I prooue.</p>
            <p>Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a|re.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>It is vniuſt to exact any money where there is no commutation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But an vſurer the principall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſafe, doth exact vſury not for any thing els, but for the duty of lending only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ergo, <hi>It is vnlawful and vniuſt to exact vſurie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>A thing that is vnfruitful by Nature is not to be tranſferred as fruitfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But money is a thing that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull by Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ergo, <hi>For the lone of Mony no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to be exacted; eſpecially the principall being ſafe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:5421:18"/>
            <p>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>The price muſt not be marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe or ware. Mony is the price. Ergo, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 The <hi>Propoſition</hi> is proued, becauſe when the price is marchandiſe, the vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alwaies gaineth ſomwhat aboue the price. So there is ſome thing added for nothing, in which there is an inequality.</p>
            <p n="8">8 The <hi>Aſſumption</hi> is apparant from the invention of Mony; Mony ought to be a rule and meaſure to apportion eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man his owne; but no marchandiſing thing.</p>
            <p>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Mony was invented for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation and exchange; not that mony ſhoulde ingender or beget mony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But in vſury there is no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> Ergo. <hi>Vſurie is vnlawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 By <hi>the lawe of God,</hi> no man may lend vpon vſurie.</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.25. <hi>If thou lende mony to my people, that is, to the poore with thee,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5421:18"/>thou ſhalt not bee as an vſurer vnto him: yee ſhall not oppreſſe him with vſurie,</hi> or <hi>impoſe vſurie vpon him</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.35 36 <hi>If thy brother bee impoueriſhed &amp; fallen in decay with thee, thou ſhalt releeue him, yea the ſtranger &amp; ſoiorner that he may liue with thee. Thou ſhalt take no vſurie of him nor vantage, but thou ſhalt feare thy God, that thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may liue with thee. Thou ſhalt not giue him thy mony to vſurie, nor lend him thy victuals for increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 Here we muſt vnderſtand, that it is not only the <hi>labourer</hi> that by his daily worke getteth his living, nor yet the <hi>meane huſband-man,</hi> that is called <hi>poore</hi> or ſaid to be impoveriſhed in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p n="14">14 But alſo the <hi>Rich Farmer,</hi> the <hi>wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Marchant,</hi> the <hi>landed Gentleman,</hi> or others of great calling, who fall into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, and wax poore, ſo that they haue as great need to borrow, as any poore labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:5421:19"/>
            <p n="15">15 So then, the meaning is, If thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (whether he be labourer, artiſicer, husband-man, Yeoman, marchant, gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tleman or noble man) be decayd, &amp; his ſtate beginne to fall:</p>
            <p n="16">16 Then thou ſhalte lende vnto him freely, to helpe him, to vpholde him, to maintaine his lawfull eſtate and calling.</p>
            <p n="17">17 <hi>Thou ſhalt not impoſe vſurie vpon him,</hi> that is, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is falling, thou ſhalt not ſtrike him down &amp; tread him vnder thy feet, but ſhalt take him by the hand, vphold him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falling, &amp; let thy ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and thy wealth ſupport his weaknes.</p>
            <p n="18">18 But <hi>ſhalt releeue him,</hi> thou ſhalte not anſwere him as Naball anſwered David, <hi>VVho is David?</hi> &amp;c. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.10. 19 <hi>Deu.</hi> 23.19.20. <hi>Thou ſhalt not giue to vſury to thy Brother: as vſurie of money, vſury of meat, vſury of anything that is put to vſury. Vnto this ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger thou mayſt le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſu. but thou ſhalt not le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury to thy brother. That the L. thy God may
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:5421:19"/>bleſse thee in al thou ſetſt thine ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to, in the land whither thou goeſt to poſſeſſe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20 In theſe wordes, there is an oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition betweene <hi>this stranger,</hi> that is, the curſed Cananites, and <hi>the Iewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21 By <hi>Stra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger</hi> in this place are meant the <hi>Hittites,</hi> the the <hi>Girgaſhites,</hi> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morites,</hi> the <hi>Cananites,</hi> the <hi>Periſites,</hi> the <hi>Hivites,</hi> and the <hi>Iebuſites,</hi> and no other ſtranger: as appeareth <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.35.</p>
            <p n="22">22 Theſe the Iſraelits were comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to deſtroy. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.27 <hi>&amp;c. Numb.</hi> 3.32. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.1.2.16.</p>
            <p>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o.</p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>That which the Lorde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Iewes to doe, for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment &amp; deſtruction of the cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed Cananites, cannot poſsiblie be turned to a bleſſing to Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But it was to lend vpon vſurie which the LORD permitted the Iewes, only to the curſed Cananits, for a kinde of puniſhment to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them with all.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:5421:20"/>
            <p>Ergo. <hi>To lend vpon vſurie ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not turne to a bleſſing vnto Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> And whoſoever lendeth to another vppon vſury, whether it be vnto rich or poore, it is to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, and to deſtroy him.</p>
            <p n="24">24 The Lord addeth <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.20. <hi>That the Lord thy God may bleſſe thee in all thou ſetteſt thine hand to;</hi> to perſwade men, freely and without vſurie to ende to them that are impoueriſhed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed.</p>
            <p n="25">25 As if the Lord had ſaid; <hi>As thou wouldeſt haue me to Bleſſe thee: So helpe thou &amp; releeue him that is decayed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">26 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.5 <hi>Hee that giveth not his money vnto vſury, nor taketh reward a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the innocent, hee that doth theſe things ſhall never fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27 <hi>Prev</hi> 28.8. <hi>He that increaſeth his riches by vſurie and increaſe, gathereth them from him that will bee mercifull to the poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:5421:20"/>
            <p n="28">28 That is, The Lord by his provide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wil defeate the Vſurer of them, &amp; giue them vnto ſuch as be more mercifull &amp; charitable. See <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.22. <hi>Iob.</hi> 20.15.</p>
            <p n="29">29 <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.10. <hi>I haue not lent vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="30">30 <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.13. <hi>Hee that hath given forth vpon vſurie, or hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> increaſes, ſhall hee liue? Hee ſhall not liue, ſeeing hee hath done this abomination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="31">31 <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.19. <hi>Hee that hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued vſury nor increaſe, he ſhall not die in the iniquity of his Father, but hee ſhall ſurelie liue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="32">32 The ſame Prophet diſplaying the tranſgreſſions of Ieruſalem ſaith. <hi>In thee haue they taken giftes to ſhedde blood, thou haſt taken vſurie, and increaſe, and thou haſt defrauded thy neighbors by extortio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and hast forgotten mee ſaith the Lorde God. Ezech.</hi> 22.12.</p>
            <p n="33">33 <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.35. <hi>Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d looking for nothing again, &amp; your reward ſhal be great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="34">34 In that Chriſt ſaith <hi>Lende,</hi> hee
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5421:21"/>biddeth not <hi>to giue,</hi> but would haue the principall to be reſtored: only he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth that nothing ſhould bee exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted more then was lent.</p>
            <p n="35">35 By <hi>the Civill lawe,</hi> it is forbidden to lend vpon vſurie 1. Becauſe the lawe ſaith <hi>That it doth not diſdaine to imitate the ſacred Canons, eſpecially in caſes con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerning Matrimonie and vſurie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="36">36. 2. Becauſe <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> ſaith that he imbraceth the 4. General Councels, &amp; in the Nicene which was one of the 4. vſury is forbidden. <hi>Diſt.</hi> 47. <hi>Ca. Quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="37">37. By <hi>the Canon lawe,</hi> it is forbidden alſo <hi>Vide Decr. Iul Gelaſ. Mart. Leonis, Cauſ.</hi> 14 q. 4 <hi>&amp; Dist.</hi> 47. <hi>c. Quoniam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="38">38. <hi>Generall Councels</hi> haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned vſurie. <hi>Concil. Arelatenſ. Terraconenſ. Agathenſ. I N Nicen. Martini Papa.</hi> Of which ſee <hi>Cauſ.</hi> 4. <hi>q.</hi> 4. Alſo <hi>Eliher. Dist.</hi> 47. <hi>Can. Siquis clericaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Furoneſ Lateran Vide Decr: Greg: l:</hi> 5: <hi>T:</hi> 19 De <hi>Vſ. C.</hi> 3. And <hi>Laod. Vide</hi> D. 49. <hi>c. Non licet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:5421:21"/>
            <p n="39">39 All the <hi>Auncient Fathers</hi> of the Church haue abhorred, and writen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Sinne: <hi>As Chriſoſt. in Oper: Imperf: Hom:</hi> 12: <hi>in Math:</hi> 5: <hi>Lactan: De Vero Cultu Lib:</hi> 6: <hi>cap:</hi> 18: <hi>Auguſt: in Pſa:</hi> 36: <hi>Hieron: lib:</hi> 6: <hi>in Ezech:</hi> 18: <hi>Leo: Ser:</hi> 6: <hi>De ieiunio decimi menſ: ca:</hi> 3: <hi>Baſil: Com in Pſal:</hi> 14: <hi>Ambroſ: lib:</hi> 6: <hi>Epiſt:</hi> 70: <hi>&amp; lib:</hi> De <hi>Tob: c:</hi> 3: 4: 5: <hi>&amp;</hi> 7:</p>
            <p n="40">40 <hi>Philoſophers</hi> haue condemned it: <hi>Plato lib:</hi> 5: <hi>De Leg. Ariſtot: lib:</hi> 1: <hi>Polit: et lib:</hi> 4: <hi>Ethic: Nich: Cicer: lib:</hi> 2: <hi>Offic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="41">41 <hi>Poets</hi> haue exclaimed againſt V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie, as <hi>Lucan. l</hi> 1. <hi>De Bell Civ.</hi> Hinc Vſura vorax auidum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> in tempore foenus, Vide L. Sex. <hi>5 T. 5.</hi> de Vſ. <hi>And</hi> Auſon. Ecl. de Amb: vi: elig: — turpia lucra Foenoris, et velox inopes <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura trucidat.</p>
            <p n="42">42: The <hi>lawes and conſtitutions of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> haue prohibited and fobiden this ſinne: 20: <hi>H:</hi> 3: <hi>cap:</hi> 5: <hi>&amp;</hi> 14: E: 3: <hi>Cap:</hi> 5: <hi>&amp;</hi> 3: <hi>H:</hi> 7: <hi>cap:</hi> 6: 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 33: <hi>H:</hi> 8: <hi>Cap:</hi> 9: <hi>&amp;</hi> 06 5: <hi>&amp;</hi> 6: E: 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. <hi>Eliz: Cap:</hi> 8:</p>
            <div n="reason" type="section">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:5421:22"/>
               <head>So much for Teſtimonies; It followeth to prooue that it is not lawfull to lend vpon vſurie by Reaſon.</head>
               <p n="43">43 <hi>Firſt</hi> then, vſurie is intollerable, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the fowle vice of Avarice is the roote of vſurie.</p>
               <p n="44">44 <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe it is wicked to deſire and exact gaine of an other mans labour.</p>
               <p n="45">45 <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe he that paieth v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie is greatly endammaged; &amp; the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer receiueth gaine without the loſſe of any of the principall, howſoever the matter goeth.</p>
               <p n="46">46 <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Becauſe vſury doth day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly torment &amp; aſſault his conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that taketh it, and extenuateth the ſubſtance of him that giveth it.</p>
               <p n="47">47 <hi>Fiftly,</hi> Becauſe there were grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous puniſhments inflicted for this ſin vpon him that was an Vſurer, by the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill</hi> &amp; <hi>Canon lawes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="48">48 By <hi>the Civil law</hi> A manifeſt Vſurer
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5421:22"/>is not capable to mak a wil of his goods. The Ancient laws of the Romans puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed a theefe with the reſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, but the Vſurer of four fold. <hi>Cato. l.</hi> 1 <hi>de re Ruſt. ca.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="49">49 By <hi>the canon law</hi> vſu. was prohibited either to the <hi>Cleargy</hi> or to the <hi>lay people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="50">50 If any of <hi>the Cleargie did</hi> take vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, he ſhould be degraded, and made it reguler <hi>Conc. Nicen.</hi> 18, <hi>Diſt.</hi> 33. <hi>c. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Diſt.</hi> 46. <hi>c. Seditio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="51">51 If any of <hi>the Laytie</hi> were an Vſurer, 1. He ſhould be ſuſpended from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
               <p n="52">52 2. He ſhould be excommunicated out of the Church.</p>
               <p n="53">53 3. Hee ſhould not bee admitted to Chriſtian Buriall <hi>Vide Decr. Greg lib.</hi> 5. <hi>tit.</hi> 19. <hi>De Vſuris. &amp; Cauſ.</hi> 14 <hi>q.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> That Vſurie is vnlawfull and damnable.</head>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:5421:23"/>
               <head>Arg. 1. A Definitione Rei.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. 1 </head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>All gaine that contrary to the word of god, is expected or exacted aboue the principall, for the very duty of lending, is vnlawfull and damnable.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vſury is ſuch a gaine, as appeareth Exod.</hi> 22.25. <hi>Lev.</hi> 25.37. <hi>Deut.</hi> 23 19. <hi>Eze.</hi> 18.8. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 15.5. <hi>Luc.</hi> 6.34.</item>
                  <item>Ergo <hi>Vſury is vnlawfull and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <head>Arg. 2. Ab Etimologia ſeu Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latione vſurae.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Dat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i. 2 </head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Appellation whereby any thing is termed doth alſo partly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the nature of the ſame.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the Appellations of vſurie, both in the old and new Teſtament do ſignifie a hurtful and monſtrous thing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ergo <hi>Vſury is hurtful &amp; mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="3">3 The <hi>Aſſumption</hi> is proved. <hi>Firſt</hi> vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in <hi>Hebrewe</hi> is tearmed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>neſhech
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5421:23"/>Exod.</hi> 22.25. which ſignifieth <hi>biting,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>naſhach, to bite,</hi> or to <hi>gnaw</hi> as Serpents and Mice doe.</p>
               <p n="4">4 As venemous <hi>Serpents</hi> do ſting and deſtroy the body with their poyſon, and as <hi>Mice</hi> if they gnaw the loafe within, they will make it become vnprofitable for the vſe of Man.</p>
               <p n="5">5 So vſury deſtroieth, biteth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth a mans ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce very ſpeedily, &amp; vexeth the body with preſent paine; &amp; poiſeneth &amp; polluteth the ſoule with the contagion of eternall damnation.</p>
               <p n="6">6 An <hi>vſurer</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>maſhich</hi> becauſe he giueth the <hi>bite:</hi> and the <hi>bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>noſhech,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>naſhuch,</hi> becauſe he is <hi>bitten.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 The ſecond appellation whereby it is called in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>tarbith, Levit.</hi> 25.36. which ſignifieth <hi>increaſe;</hi> derived of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ravah, to be multiplied, to grow, or increaſe, Deut.</hi> 30.16.</p>
               <p n="8">8 It is ſo called becauſe vſurers at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5421:24"/>increaſe and multiplication vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a thing vnfruitfull by Nature, which neither can increaſe nor multiplie: and this by the teſtimony of the Ethnickes, is contrary vnto Nature &amp; monſtrous.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Vſuries are alſo called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>techa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim,</hi> which ſignifieth <hi>Deceits, Pſal.</hi> 72.14. derived of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>tachach deceipt,</hi> or <hi>frawd,</hi> becauſe vſurie is neuer without deceipt.</p>
               <p n="10">10 In <hi>Greeke</hi> vſurie is tearmed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is derived of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to bring forth,</hi> or <hi>to beget.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11 It is alſo called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>increaſe,</hi> which tearmes doe not obſcurely note the monſtruoſitie of it.</p>
               <p n="12">12 In <hi>Latin</hi> it is called <hi>Foenus, quaſi foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> encreaſe as it were a childe, or thing begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; <hi>vſura quaſi propter vſum res,</hi> Vſurie as it were for the vſe of a thing.</p>
               <p n="13">13 <hi>Becauſe</hi> contrary vnto nature mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny being a thing vnfruitfull, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled as it were, to beget &amp; bring forth fruit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:5421:24"/>
               <head>Arg. 3. A Coniugatis.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Syllogiſmus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexus primo modo.</head>
                  <item>14 <hi>If vſurers be excluded from Iehovah his tabernacle;</hi> Ergo <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury is a thing vnlawfull and da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But the Antecedent is true: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth Pſal.</hi> 15.5.</item>
                  <item>Ergo. <hi>The Conſequent is true alſo.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <head>Arg. 4. A toto &amp; partibus.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Enthymema.</head>
                  <item>15 <hi>To vſurie there wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall part of a Contract,</hi> vid. <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe or ware:</hi> for a Contract is <hi>Actus contra actum,</hi> where there is <hi>Quid pro quo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ergo. <hi>It is no contract;</hi> and ſo a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous and an vnlawfull thing.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="16">16 The Argument holdeth for <hi>one principall part being deſtroied, the whole is deſtroied.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="argument">
               <head>Arg. 5. A Diviſione.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j.</head>
                  <item>17 <hi>To condemne thoſe thinges, which are forbidden by the lawe of Nature, by the lawe of God, by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5421:25"/>the lawes Civill and Canon, and by many godly conſtitutions of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces both ancient and late, is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, godlie, and iuſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But to take any thing aboue the principall for the lone only, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by all theſe lawes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ergo, <hi>The condemnation of vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is neceſsary godly and iuſt.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="argument">
               <head>Arg 6. A Cauſis.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</head>
                  <item>18 <hi>Of what thing ſo ever the cauſes are evill that thing it ſelfe is evill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vſurie is a thing whoſe cauſes are evill; as is declared before. Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Poſit.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ergo, <hi>Vſurie it ſelfe is evill.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="argument">
               <head>Arg 7. Ab Effectis.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</head>
                  <item>19 <hi>That thing whoſe effects are evill, is alſo evill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Vſurie is ſuch a thing, as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Poſit.</hi> 2.</item>
                  <item>Ergo, <hi>Vſurie is evill.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="argument">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:5421:25"/>
               <head>Arg. 8. Ab abſurdis.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j.</head>
                  <item>20 <hi>That which being taught and received, many abſurdities and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences doe follovve, connot be true, certaine, and firme.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But out of that doctrine vvhich teacheth that it is lawfull to take vſury ariſe many abſurditres.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ergo, <hi>That doctrine that permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vſury, is neither true, certein, nor firme;</hi> but falſe and into era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Church.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="21">The <hi>Aſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> is manifeſt for <hi>firſt,</hi> It is againſt the manifeſt text of Scripture</p>
               <p n="22">22 2. It extinguiſheth faith &amp; charity</p>
               <p n="23">23 <hi>Thirdlie,</hi> It taketh away the law of nature.</p>
               <p n="24">24 <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It annihilateth the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſtitutions of Princes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="argument">
               <head>Arg 9. A Neceſſario.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j.</head>
                  <item>25 <hi>The commandements of God are neceſſarily to be obeyed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But God hath commanded to lend
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5421:26"/>looking for nothing for the leaue: Luk:</hi> 6: 34:</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo, we muſt doe ſo.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="argument">
               <head>Arg: 10: Ab Impoſſibili:</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent:</head>
                  <item>26 <hi>It is impoſſible that faith &amp; an evill Conſcience ſhoulde at the ſame inſtance be ioyned togither, in the ſame man.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>All Vſurers haue an evill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ergo, <hi>No Vſurer hath faith.</hi> And conſequently it is impoſſible for them that wittingly and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſeuere in this ſinne to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</item>
               </list>
               <p n="27">27 The <hi>Aſſumption</hi> appeareth becauſe the <hi>Vſurers</hi> ſinne againſt their own con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience; which is manifeſt.</p>
               <p n="28">28 <hi>Firſt,</hi> becauſe they will not willing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly be known to be <hi>Vſurers:</hi> yea ſome will ſweare and ſtare they are no ſuch men.</p>
               <p n="29">29 And therfore they coniure faithfull ſecrecy of the borrower, or they colour
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:5421:26"/>their vſury vnder pretence of ſome law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full contract.</p>
               <p n="30">30 <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe that though they be knowne and reputed for <hi>common vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> yet they take it a great diſgrace ſo to be called and tearmed of others.</p>
               <p n="31">31 <hi>Thirdly,</hi> becauſe they will not call vſurie, <hi>vſurie,</hi> but <hi>vſance, intereſt,</hi> or <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſideration,</hi> being indeed aſhamed of the direct name of <hi>vſurie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="32">32 So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Vſurers ſinne willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and of ſet purpoſe, they followe a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe contrary to the checke, touch, and light of their owne conſcience; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as Paule ſpeaketh they are damned of themſelues: <hi>Tit:</hi> 3: 11.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="argument">
               <head>Arg: 11: A minori ad maius:</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Enth:</head>
                  <item>33 <hi>Theft is vnlawfull &amp; damnable:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ergo, much more is vſurie ſo.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <item>34 The <hi>Conſequence</hi> is good, becauſe <hi>vſurers</hi> doe ſteale daily without ceaſing having no need: <hi>Theeues</hi> ſteal but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, being vrged by neceſſity: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5421:27"/>
                     <hi>Vſurers</hi> are worthy of greater pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment then <hi>Theeues</hi> are.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="argument">
               <head>Arg. 12. A Contrario.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Enthymema.</head>
                  <item>35 <hi>To help &amp; to deſtroy are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traries.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ergo, <hi>They cannot bee both at once, at the ſame time, &amp; in the ſame reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect attributed to the ſame man.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Therfore that bragge of the <hi>Vſurer</hi> is an impudentlie, when he boaſteth that oftentimes he helpeth and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richeth them that he lendeth mony vnto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="argument">
               <head>Arg. 13. Ab Oppoſitis.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Syllogiſmus connexus primo modo.</head>
                  <item>36 <hi>There are two kingdomes, the kingdome of God, and the kingdome of the Divell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But in the kingdome of GOD there is no ſinne, and vſurie is a ſinne.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ergo, <hi>It followeth that all vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers as long as they do not repent &amp; leaue their ſinne, are of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Divell.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="argument">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:5421:27"/>
               <head>Arg. 14. A Natura Relativorum.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Enthymema:</head>
                  <item>37 <hi>In le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding there is no marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ergo, <hi>There muſt no price be paide.</hi> For he that aſketh a price giving no marchandiſe for the ſame is a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable vſurer.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="argument">
               <head>Arg. 15. Ab Exemplo.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Enthymema.</head>
                  <item>38 <hi>Nehemias did well in prohibiting vſurie. Neh.</hi> 5.7.11.</item>
                  <item>Ergo, <hi>Thoſe Magiſtrates which prohibite and repreſſe vſurie doe well likewiſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="argument">
               <head>Arg. 16. ab Authoritate ſacrae ſcripturae.</head>
               <list type="syllogism">
                  <head>Enthymema.</head>
                  <item>39 <hi>Neither did the Prophets, nor Chriſt, nor the Apoſtles ever allowe and grant that vſury is lawfull, but rather they prohibited and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ergo, <hi>They who either allow or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit vſury, do by a wicked &amp; raſh pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption departe from the veritie of the Scriptures, &amp; contemne the worde of God.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:5421:28"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> How great a ſinne vſury is.</head>
            <p n="1">1 THe grievouſnes of this ſinne ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the <hi>Effects</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>Effects of vſury,</hi> are to be conſidered, either in reſpect <hi>of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer,</hi> or in reſpect <hi>of the Borrower.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>In reſpect of the vſurer,</hi> the <hi>effects</hi> are;</p>
            <p n="4">4 Goods gotten by deceite and guile, by robborie, ſacriledge and murder.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The perturbation and breaking of ſocietie.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The wrath of God, malediction, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill conſcience, the tyrannie of Satan.</p>
            <p n="7">7 The murdering of the poore; the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying of other mens liues.</p>
            <p n="8">8 A riotous and tragicall ſpending of goods after the <hi>vſurers</hi> death.</p>
            <p n="9">9 The ſubiecting of goods to maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Eternal da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of body &amp; ſoul; &amp;c</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:5421:28"/>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>In reſpect of the Borrower,</hi> the <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects</hi> are;</p>
            <p n="12">12 Poverty, hunger and thirſt, naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, griefe, death, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Vſury is compared to <hi>a ſhip wrack,</hi> wherein nothing is ſaued, becauſe the vſurer conſumeth all.</p>
            <p n="14">14 To <hi>a raging fire,</hi> that never ceaſeth before all the houſe be devoured.</p>
            <p n="15">15 To <hi>dunge,</hi> into which if any man fall, he muſt either ſpeedily run away, or lie very ſtill, or els he ſhall be all mirie: ſo a man muſt haue no dealing with vſury.</p>
            <p n="16">16 To the <hi>ſtinging of Serpents:</hi> for v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie ſo poiſoneth a mans ſubſtance that it ſhall haue the rot, and conſume away.</p>
            <p n="17">17 To a <hi>deadly and contagious Ague,</hi> whereby the poore are caſt into ſhaking fits, and at laſt conſumed, and pined to the bones.</p>
            <p n="18">18 To <hi>a gulfe or whirle poole,</hi> which devoureth ſoules, and vtterly waſteth wealth.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:5421:29"/>
            <p n="19">19 An <hi>Vſurer</hi> is <hi>a theefe,</hi> becauſe hee ſtealeth from the poore borrower that little he hath.</p>
            <p n="20">20 An <hi>Vſurer</hi> is <hi>a ravenous vulture,</hi> that will picke the guttes out of a mans bellie.</p>
            <p n="21">21 An <hi>Vſurer</hi> is <hi>a Murderer,</hi> becauſe with a age cruelty, he eateth up, &amp; ſlay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth the borrower &amp; his familie, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhould releeue with al works of charity.</p>
            <p n="22">22 An <hi>Vſurer</hi> is an <hi>Idolater,</hi> for hee is covetous, and covetouſnes is Idolatry, <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 5.5: <hi>Coloſſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5.</p>
            <p n="23">23 And <hi>Vſurer</hi> is like vnto <hi>the Devil,</hi> who continually ſeeketh whome to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; ſo the <hi>Vſurer</hi> night &amp; day ſtil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth the <hi>borrower</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24 What <hi>wickednes</hi> then is VSVRIE wherein at once <hi>woefull ſhip wracke, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging fire, filthie dunge, venemous poyſon, contagious ſicknes, &amp; a devouring gulfe,</hi> is cauſed by a <hi>Theefe, a ravenous Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a Murderer, an Idolater,</hi> and one
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5421:29"/>that is <hi>like vnto the Divel</hi> himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="25">25 <hi>Vſury</hi> is ſuch a darte that the <hi>Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> therewith ſtriketh without a weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he menaceth without handling, &amp; ſtay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth without touching the body.</p>
            <p n="26">26 <hi>David</hi> ioineth <hi>vſury</hi> with <hi>deceipt,</hi> becauſe vſury is never without deceipt. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 55:11.</p>
            <p n="27">27 <hi>Ezechiell</hi> calleth him vniuſt that lendeth vpon vſurie. <hi>Ezech:</hi> 18: 8.</p>
            <p n="28">28 Vſury is an abominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Ezec.</hi> 18.13</p>
            <p n="29">29 The Lord wil take away from the Vſurer even that he hath, &amp; giue it him which wil bee mercifull to the poore. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28: 8.</p>
            <p n="30">30 Vſury excludeth and ſhuteth him that practiſeth it, from entering into Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah his tabernacle, and from reſting in his holy mountaine. <hi>Pſal:</hi> 15, 5.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> Obiections for vſury anſwered.</head>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:5421:30"/>
            <p>OBiect: 1: <hi>God alloweth ſome kinde of vſurie for Deut:</hi> 23: 20: <hi>it is ſaide: Of a ſtraunger thou maieſt take vſurie</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Anſw:</hi> But thou takeſt vſury of thy <hi>brother,</hi> therfore this condemneth thee, becauſe thou vſeſt thy <hi>brother</hi> like a <hi>ſtranger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 By the name of <hi>Straunger</hi> in that place are ſignified the curſed Cananits: <hi>See Cap:</hi> 4: <hi>Poſit:</hi> 21: So alſo doth <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ: lib:</hi> De <hi>Tobia, cap:</hi> 15: <hi>Paulus Fagius Annot: in Caldaic: Paraphraſ: in Deut:</hi> 23: 20: <hi>Tremel: &amp; Iunius Anot: in Deut:</hi> 23: 20: expound it.</p>
            <p n="4">God doth not licenſe the Iewes to take vſurie of any, but of their enemies whom they might kill.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Shewing that <hi>vſury</hi> is ſuch a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as if we are <hi>to kill a man,</hi> it were a fit puniſhment for him.</p>
            <p n="6">6 But nowe, wee are alone body, wee haue alone ſpirite, one hope of our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5421:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>one Lord, one faith, one Baptiſme, one GOD and Father of al, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all, and through all, and in vs all.</p>
            <p>Therfore amongſt vs there is <hi>no ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 Obiect: 2: <hi>The Law of Moſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vſury, is only politicall. Therfore we are not bound to it further then equity &amp; humanity permitteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>Anſw:</hi> It is not politicall, but mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall: The law ſaith, <hi>Exod:</hi> 22: 25: <hi>Yee ſhall not oppreſse him with vſury:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a breach of the moral law <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurie is Oppreſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ergo, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurie is a breach of the moral law</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>David Pſal:</hi> 15: 5: reckoneth it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong morall duties:</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Ezechiel</hi> hedgeth it in betweene <hi>Bribery</hi> &amp; <hi>Extortio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> which are notorious breaches of the moral law: <hi>Ezec:</hi> 22: 12:</p>
            <p n="12">12 Obiect: 3: <hi>The law forbiddeth len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon vſury to the poore and needie ONLY, Exod:</hi> 22: 25: <hi>Levit:</hi> 25: 35.</p>
            <p n="13">13 <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is no good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5421:31"/>that he might borrow vpon vſurie, then that he might not borrow at all.</p>
            <p n="19">19 God in the lawes of vſurie did ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially &amp; by name forbid lending in that manner <hi>to the poore</hi> for two reſpects.</p>
            <p n="20">20 <hi>Firſt,</hi> to ſhew what care HE HIM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SELFE hath over them, who are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly and vſually neglected of men.</p>
            <p n="21">21 <hi>Secondly,</hi> becauſe the poore are ſoneſt &amp; eaſieſt oppreſſed of the rich; as the loweſt hedg is eaſieſt ſtepped over.</p>
            <p n="22">22 Ob. 4. <hi>Moſes ſaith, Exod.</hi> 22.25. <hi>Yee ſhall not oppreſſe him with vſurie.</hi> Ergo, <hi>If I oppreſse not my brother with bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vſurie; I may take ſome vſurie and increaſe of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23 <hi>Anſ.</hi> All vſury biteth; and therefore all vſury is vnlawfull, albeit one biteth ſooner then an other, &amp; one ſooner per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived then another.</p>
            <p n="24">24 But to remoue this excuſe from vs; god hath forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>al increaſe for le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding,</hi> and that in all things that may bee lent
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5421:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>A man may not take vſury of the Poore:</hi> Ergo, <hi>he may take of the rich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.22. <hi>Rob not the poore becauſe hee is poore.</hi> Shall I thence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude; Ergo, <hi>I may rob the rich becauſe he is rich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 The law ſaith, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.24. <hi>Curſed be he that ſmiteth his neighbour ſecretly.</hi> Shal I thence conclude; Ergo, <hi>It is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for a man to ſmite his neighbor ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16 Moreover, if the law of lending to the poore without vſury, ſhould inferre the lawfulnes of lending to the rich vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſurie: It is manifeſt that Gods inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in that place, for the benefit of the pore; ſhould rather proue an hurt and hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance vnto them; becauſe by this means it woulde come to paſſe, that the poore ſhould not borrow at all.</p>
            <p n="17">17 For who would lend <hi>to the poore</hi> for nothing, that coulde lawfully lend <hi>vnto the rich</hi> for vſurie?</p>
            <p n="18">18 Surely it were better for the poore
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5421:32"/>by mutuation. <hi>Lev.</hi> 25.36.37. <hi>Thou ſhalt take no vſurie of him nor vantage. Thou ſhalt not giue him thy mony to vſurie, nor lend him thy victuals for increaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">25 Ezechiel condemneth the people of his time, not only for taking vſury, but alſo for taking of increaſe. <hi>Ezec.</hi> 22.12. <hi>Thou haſt taken vſurie, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">26 Ob. 5. <hi>Vſurie is no where prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the new Teſt.</hi> Ergo, <hi>It is lawfull, or at leaſt wiſe tolerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27 <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is a monſtrous blaſphemie againſt the Goſpell of Chriſt, to affirme that the New Teſt giveth more libertie to ſinne, then the old.</p>
            <p n="28">28 Yet this obiection thinketh <hi>Vſury is no ſin,</hi> becauſe it is not condemned in the new Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="29">29 But that is no good Argument, for <hi>Poligamie, Tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, Treaſon, Ielouſie, &amp;c.</hi> are ſinnes, and manifeſt breaches of the morall law; and yet they are not conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5421:32"/>by thoſe verie names in the Newe Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="30">30 Furthermore; Vſurie is forbidden in the New Teſt. For the Goſpell goeth further in this caſe, then the law. The law <hi>forbiddeth vſurie:</hi> but the Goſpell <hi>commandeth the contrary vertue,</hi> that is, <hi>free lending without increaſe. Luc.</hi> 6.35.</p>
            <p n="31">31 Alſo, vſurie is manifeſtly againſt theſe places. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.12 <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.42. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.28.</p>
            <p n="32">32 Ob. 6. The vſurer ſaith, <hi>I lende for compaſſion; and by my mony many are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, and the poore thereby avoide dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">33 <hi>Anſ.</hi> To be partaker in our <hi>gaines,</hi> &amp; not in our <hi>loſſes</hi> is <hi>Vſurers compaſſion</hi> and charitie.</p>
            <p n="34">34 The good that Vſurers doe vnto the poore is like the good Men in hoate agues haue of drinking colde water, which for a time refreſheth, but at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth increaſeth their paine, and prolongeth the diſeaſe.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:5421:33"/>
            <p n="35">35 So at the beginning, vſury is mild, but in the end, it is mercileſſe.</p>
            <p n="36">36 The Vſurer pleadeth loue, but not for thy ſake, but for his owne: as the Ivy colleth &amp; claſpeth the Oake, as a Lover. but thereby it groweth vp, and overtop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peth the oake, and ſucketh vp the iuice and ſap therof, that it cannot thriue nor proſper: Such a <hi>bloud ſucker</hi> is the <hi>Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="37">37 The vvoorme <hi>Teredo</hi> is ſofte to touch, but it hath ſuch harde teeth as it devoureth and conſumeth the harde timber: So the Vſurer is a ſoft beaſt at the firſt to handle, but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of time, the hardneſſe of his teeth will eate a man vp, fleſh and bone, if hee haue not an eſpecial regard to ſhunne him.</p>
            <p n="38">38 The <hi>Catte</hi> playeth vvith the <hi>Mouſe;</hi> But the playe of the Catte is the death of the Mouſe: So the <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer</hi> pleaſeth the <hi>Borrovver;</hi> But the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:5421:33"/>pleaſure of the Vſurer is the bane of the Borrower.</p>
            <p n="39">39 The <hi>Scorpion</hi> laugheth when hee ſtriketh, and the Crocodile vveepeth when he wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth: So the <hi>Vſurer</hi> laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and then oppreſſeth: hee pittieth &amp; then he pintcheth the poore <hi>Borrovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="40">40 Obiection. 7. <hi>I doe not ſinne</hi> ſaith the Vſurer, <hi>nor breake the rule of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: I doe to others, as I deſire that others ſhoulde doe vnto mee, as Chriſt bad vs. I would with all my hearte, giue ten in the hundred, if I vveere forced to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="41">41 <hi>Aunſwere</hi> No man woulde giue 10 in the hundred, if hee could tel howe to borrowe freely: but ſeeing they can get it no better they are content to giue ten.</p>
            <p n="42">42 That ſaying of our Saviour Chriſt. <hi>VVhat ſoever yee vvoulde that men &amp;c.</hi> muſt bee vnderſtood of good thinges
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:5421:34"/>
               <hi>onelie,</hi> or elſe many abſurdities ſhoulde follow; as,</p>
            <p n="43">43 <hi>I would that ſome man vvoulde kill me. Ergo, I may kill another in like maner.</hi> As many a deſperate man with all his hart wiſheth.</p>
            <p n="44">44 Wherefore, ſeeing to take vppon vſury, 10: for the 100: is not ſimply good, but leſſe-evill, then to take 16.20.30. or more: Therefore albeit thou for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gaine, or vpon extreame neceſſity, to avoide a further miſciefe, ſometimes wouldeſt giue ſo to others, yet ſhall not that excuſe thee, ſo to take vſurie of thy poore and needy brother.</p>
            <p n="45">45 Obiect. 8. <hi>Vſury is neceſſary for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans, VVidowes, and Strangers vvhich haue no other vvaye to gette their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="46">46 <hi>Anſw.</hi> If vſury be evill in it ſelfe, and condemned by God; then can it not be good in any. For what is ſimply evill, is evill in all, albeit in ſome more, and in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:5421:34"/>other leſſe evill.</p>
            <p n="47">47 <hi>Rom,</hi> 3.8. <hi>VVe muſt not do evil that good may come therof.</hi> Therfore we muſt not releeue the fatherleſſe &amp; widdowes by vſurie.</p>
            <p n="48">48 Obiect. 9: <hi>The Vſurer will ſay, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſse I haue no other trade to liue vpon I muſt therefore liue by vſury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="49">49 <hi>Anſ.</hi> So may the Theefe ſay; <hi>Alas I haue no other trade but robbing, I muſt therfore liue by that.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="50">50 This excuſe in other wickedneſſe wil not ſerue. Therfore neither in vſury.</p>
            <p n="51">51 Obiect. 10: <hi>The lawes of the lande do allow to take</hi> 10: <hi>in the</hi> 100: <hi>Ergo I may take ſo much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="52">52 <hi>Anſw.</hi> The law of MAN cannot abrogate or diſanull the law of GOD.</p>
            <p n="33">33 The Vſurer herein is like the Iewes, who ſaide <hi>VVe haue a law, and by our law he ſhall die, Iob</hi> 19.7. when they coulde not ſay, <hi>By Gods law he ſhall die:</hi> they ſaide <hi>By our law he ſhall die.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:5421:35"/>
            <p n="54">54 So when the vſurer cannot ſay, <hi>By Gods law I may take vſurie;</hi> He ſaith, <hi>By mans law I may take vſury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="55">55 As it would not ſerue Adams turne to ſay, <hi>The woman had me;</hi> So will it not ſerue the vſurers turne, to ſay, <hi>The Law doth licence me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="56">56 Yet herein the vſurer ſtandreth our law, for the law alloweth not 10. in the 100. nor 5. in the 100. but puniſheth that <hi>Tyrant</hi> that exacteth aboue 10. in the 100.</p>
            <p n="57">57 Ob. 11. <hi>Many learned Divines do tolorate vſurie, &amp; write in defence of it.</hi> Ergo, <hi>It is not vnlawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="58">58 <hi>Anſwere.</hi> No writer that ever I coulde ſee, or heare of, euer allowed V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVRIE.</p>
            <p n="59">59 There are many ſtrong poyſons, which the learned Phiſitian can ſo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie, that a ſicke Perſon may take a poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wherein ſome of the poiſon is.</p>
            <p n="60">60 So holy men of God haue done,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5421:35"/>and doe temper and qual fie the vſurers poiſon, that they make therof a holſome medicine for many diſtreſſed Perſons.</p>
            <p n="61">61 For by their holy and religious ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veats, and leſſons, they alter the qualitie of the vſury, and make it indeed <hi>no vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie at all,</hi> but a lawfull kinde of trade and dealing.</p>
            <p n="62">62 Firſt they teach, <hi>That a man muſt take nothing, but that which his Debter can get by good and lawfull meanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="63">63 Secondly. <hi>Hee may not take more then the gaine, nay not all the gaine, nor that part of the gaine which drinketh vp the living of him that vſeth the mony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="64">64 Thirdly. <hi>He muſt ſometimes bee ſo farre from taking gaine, that he muſt not</hi> REQVIRE THE PRINCIPALL, <hi>if his debter by inevitable &amp; iuſt cauſes be brought behinde hand, and it bee alſo plaine that hee coulde not make, no not by great diligence, any commodity of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney borrowed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:5421:36"/>
            <p n="65">65 Now, how fare VSVRIE differeth from this kind of dealing, if our commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Vſurers</hi> will not confeſſe, woefull expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience daily teacheth.</p>
            <p n="66">66 Obiect. 12. <hi>Laſtly the Vſurer vvill ſay: If I may not gaine by money vvhich I lend, I will lend no more, but keepe my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to my ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="67">67 <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is as bad to keepe thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from him that hath neede, as to le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon vſury: For Chriſt ſaith: <hi>From him that borroweth turne not away thy face. Math.</hi> 45: 42.</p>
            <p n="68">68 As hee that keepeth his corne, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vſe of his neighbours and brethren. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11: 26: is accurſed: So is hee alſo accurſed that keepeth his money, when ſafely he might lend it: <hi>Ezech:</hi> 18: Looke <hi>Eſa:</hi> 5; 8: <hi>Habac:</hi> 2: 9: <hi>Mich:</hi> 2: 2: 3: <hi>Luke</hi> 6: 24: <hi>Math:</hi> 6: 19: <hi>Iames</hi> 5: 1: <hi>Dent:</hi> 15: 8 <hi>Pſal:</hi> 112: 5. <hi>Math:</hi> 5: 42: <hi>Luke</hi> 6: 35.</p>
            <p n="69">69 That ſervant that hid &amp; laid vp his Talent was puniſhed; <hi>Math:</hi> 25: 14: 30.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:5421:36"/>And hee that will not vſe his money ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of charity, ſhall bee plagued with the wicked ſervant:</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> VVhether it be is a mans owne free choice, to lend, or noe.</head>
            <p>THe Children of this worlde, that thinke their vvealth their ovvne, iudg it to be free from them, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther they lend or no; and thinke they do not ſin, when they deny him that come to borrow of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they can helpe him.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>Lord</hi> ſaith <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Thou ſhalt open thine hand vnto him, and ſhalt lende him ſufficient for his neede vvhich hee hath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Chriſt</hi> alſo ſaith <hi>Math:</hi> 5: 42. <hi>Giue to him that asketh, &amp; from him that would borrow of thee, turne not away.</hi> See <hi>Luke</hi> 6: 34: 38.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:5421:37"/>
            <p n="4">4 Here we muſt conſider two things, <hi>Firſt,</hi> How wee muſt lend? <hi>Secondly,</hi> Vnto whom?</p>
            <p n="5">5 For the <hi>firſt,</hi> CHRIST requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of his Children that they helpe their brethren, and neighboures; not onely freelie, without any gaine, (<hi>for ſo doe the Sinners, Luke</hi> 6.34.) but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo though it be to their loſſe and damage of the money lent.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Chriſt putteth a differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce between his children and ſuch as doe not apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto him.</p>
            <p n="7">7 The Sinners are ſo iuſt, that they wil lend without vſury, deſiring nothing but onely their owne gaine.</p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>For even Sinners</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>lende vnto ſinners to receive</hi> (not anie increaſe or vantage or anie thing aboue the prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cipall, but) <hi>the like</hi> Luk. 6.34.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Out of this place, we that beare the liverey of Chriſts na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, &amp; haue vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>an holy profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may learn how we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:5421:37"/>ought to lend, vnto our needy brother, and whether we ought to take vſurie of him, or no.</p>
            <p n="10">10 For the <hi>Second. Vnto vvhom vvee ought to lend?</hi> we ought to lend: namely,</p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>Vnto them,</hi> that haue not ſo much wealth as they are able to make reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>For Sinners lende vnto them of whome they hope to receiue, againe vvhat they lent Luc.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Not onely vnto our Frends, kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and brothers; but alſo <hi>vnto Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> yea and <hi>to our Enemies. For ſinners lende vnto their friendes and kinſmen. Luc.</hi> 6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="14">14 <hi>Vnto them,</hi> who are not able to giue vs thankes, much leſſe to make vs recompenſe. <hi>For Sinners lende vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are able to thanke them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 If we lend vnto ſuch; then ſhal we verely declare our ſelues, to be his ſons, <hi>who letteth his Sun ſhine vppon the iuſt</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:5421:38"/>and vniuſt alike, and letteth his raine fal vpon the kind and vnkind.</p>
            <p n="15">15 This is it that Chriſt requireth of vs: <hi>Lende</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>looking for nothing againe, and your rewarde ſhall bee greate: and yee ſhall bee the children of the moſt High, for he is kinde vnto the vnkinde &amp; to the evill. Luc.</hi> 6.35.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 9.</hi> VVhether it bee lawfull to borrow vpon vſurie.</head>
            <p>Becauſe in theſe daies Charitie is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther DEAD then COLDE, Men muſt either borrow vpon vſurie, or they ſhall haue nothing lent them at all.</p>
            <p n="2">2 There bee <hi>tvvo ſortes of Borrowers vpon vſurie,</hi> ſome <hi>RICH,</hi> and ſome <hi>POORE.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:5421:38"/>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>The Rich</hi> borrow becauſe they would be richer, and richeſt of all.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And theſe are either <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> or <hi>Tradeſmen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Gentlemen, &amp; cuntrey Farmers,</hi> they borrow vpon vſurie, to purchaſe lands, and to enrich their poſterities.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>Tradeſ-men, and Marchantes,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy al the mony they can borrow, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to get more by the vſe of it, then the vſurie of it commeth vnto.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Theſe Rich-men,<note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> 
               <hi>may not lawfully borrow vpon vſurie</hi> as may appeare. 1. <hi>By the Cauſe</hi> that moveth them to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. 2. <hi>By the Effectes</hi> that follow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p n="8">8 The <hi>Cauſe that moveth Rich-men to borrow vpon vſurie</hi> is, their covetous greedy Minde, that like Salomons <hi>hoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leech,</hi> never crieth <hi>Inough,</hi> but <hi>Giue, giue</hi> They purchaſe all the lande they can compaſſe, &amp; make a pray of their poore Neighbours.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:5421:39"/>
            <p n="9">9 The <hi>effectes</hi> that enſue of their bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing are either <hi>common vnto all theſe borrowers,</hi> or <hi>proper to each one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>The common Effects</hi> are theſe:</p>
            <p n="11">11 1. They feede the vſurers, as the bellowes doe kindle the fire; they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them, as the Receiuer maintaines the Theefe.</p>
            <p n="12">12 2. They vndoe the Poore. For they giue ſo exceſſiuelie much for the loane of money, that either they muſt giue vp houſe-keeping, or diminiſh their hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Whereby it commeth to paſſe, that the poore are neither ſet on worke, nor relieued by the Rich.</p>
            <p n="14">14 The <hi>Effects, proper to each one</hi> are:</p>
            <p n="15">15 1. <hi>The Gentleman</hi> that borroweth vpon vſurie, racketh his rentes, and ſo maketh his poore Tenauntes pay the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie.</p>
            <p n="16">16 2. <hi>The Farmer, or Yeoman</hi> ſelleth his corne, and his cattell ſo much the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:5421:39"/>and maketh the buyer pay his v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie.</p>
            <p n="17">17 3. The <hi>Tradeſ-man, &amp; Marchant</hi> inhaunce the price of their ware, and who ſo needes their marchandiſe, muſt pay their vſurie.</p>
            <div n="the poor" type="section">
               <head>So much of Rich Borrowers vpon vſurie: Now of the Poore.</head>
               <p n="18">18 The <hi>Poore Borrowers vpon vſury,</hi> are either <hi>Counterfeites;</hi> or <hi>Poore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19 <hi>Counterfeites,</hi> are they that would ſeeme barer and needier then they are, and that for two reſpects.</p>
               <p n="20">20 <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe they would not bee deepely charged with Subſidies.</p>
               <p n="21">21 <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe they would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde with their Creditours for little or nothing.</p>
               <p n="22">22 Theſe are they, whom <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh of, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.7. <hi>There is that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himſelfe poore, having great riches.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:5421:40"/>
               <p n="23">23 Theſe are thoſe <hi>Foxes</hi> that hauing wealth inough to pay their debte, lie in Priſon, becauſe they woulde defraude their Creditours.</p>
               <p n="34">34 Theſe Counterfeites wil haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſome thing for vſurie, that men may thinke them bare of mony, and pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty them in their charges.</p>
               <p n="25">25 <hi>Poore indeede,</hi> are they which bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to ſupply their neceſſity; when they are like to bee vndone, their children to be caſt away, &amp; their leaſe to bee forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p n="26">26 This neceſſitie is either <hi>extreame neceſſitie,</hi> or <hi>not ſo extreame.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> It is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to borrow in any of both. See <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Poſit.</hi> 13.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="27">27 <hi>For neceſſitie</hi> it was lawfull for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams Sons</hi> to marry with <hi>Adams Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi> becauſe there were no other wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               <p n="28">28 <hi>For neceſſity,</hi> it was lawfull for <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> to eat the <hi>Shewbread;</hi> becauſe there
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:5421:40"/>no other food. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.6.</p>
               <p n="29">29 <hi>For neceſſity,</hi> it was lawful <hi>to work, to heale &amp; to fight vpon the Sabbath day;</hi> which was not lawful but for Neceſſity. <hi>Luc.</hi> 13.10.</p>
               <p n="30">30 Therefore <hi>for neceſſity,</hi> why may not a Man <hi>pay more then hee borrowed?</hi> Seeing no Scripture forbiddeth to pay more, but to require more.</p>
               <p n="31">31 Yet with this caveat,<note n="*" place="margin">Note wel.</note> 
                  <hi>that the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower intice not any man, to become an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer,</hi> that is, vnwilling to exerciſe that curſed Trade.</p>
               <p n="32">32 The Vſurer muſt be willing to lend for vſurie, otherwiſe the borrower doth grievouſly ſinne, notwithſtanding his neceſſitie.</p>
               <p n="33">33 Here will be Obiections made, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt borrowing vpon vſurie.</p>
               <p n="34">34 <hi>Ob.</hi> 1. Ieremy ſaith, <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.10. <hi>I haue not lent vpon vſurie to others, neither haue others lent vpon vſury to mee: as though it were vnlawfull not only to take
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:5421:41"/>vſury, but alſo to giue vſurie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="35">35 <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thereby <hi>Ieremy</hi> doth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, that he was no medler in the world, whereby they ſhould envy HIM like other men; and therefore hee cleereth himſelfe cheefely from vſurie, becauſe Vſurers were moſt envied.</p>
               <p n="36">36 And to ſhew that he was no <hi>Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi> he ſaith he was no <hi>Borrower;</hi> which is more lawfull, then to be an Vſurer.</p>
               <p n="37">37 Like a man, which ſaith, <hi>I doe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hate him nor know him:</hi> &amp; to proue that he doth not <hi>hate him;</hi> he ſaith, hee doth not <hi>know him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="38">38 So <hi>Ieremie,</hi> to proue that hee had not <hi>lent vpon vſurie,</hi> ſaith that he <hi>never borrowed</hi> vpon vſurie, nor had any dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with it.</p>
               <p n="39">39 Obiect. 2. <hi>Chriſt did caſt out the buyers out of the Temple as wel as the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="40">40 <hi>Anſw.</hi> But that was not for buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but for buying in the temple where
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:5421:41"/>they ſhould not buy but pray.</p>
               <p n="41">41 Obiect. 3. <hi>It is a common proverbe: If there were no buyers there would be no ſellers: if there were no brib-givers, there would be no bribe-takers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="42">42 <hi>Anſ.</hi> But in this caſe, it may bee rather ſaid; if there were <hi>no Takers,</hi> ther would be <hi>no Givers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="43">43 For the <hi>Giver</hi> doth not make the <hi>Receiver</hi> to take: but the <hi>Receiver</hi> doth make the <hi>Giver</hi> to give; becauſe hee wil not lend, vnleſſe the other wil giue him for the loane.</p>
               <p n="44">44 Therfore as we ſay, <hi>The receiver makes the theefe:</hi> So may we ſay, <hi>The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer of vſury makes the giver of vſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="45">45 There is no compariſon betweene him that <hi>giveth vſurie,</hi> and him that <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiveth vſury.</hi> The ONE doth it for co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vetouſnes, and the OTHER of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</p>
               <p n="46">46 He which <hi>lendeth for vſurie,</hi> len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for covetouſnes: but he which <hi>bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roweth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:5421:42"/>upon vſury,</hi> borroweth for nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſity.</p>
               <p n="46">46 <hi>Laban</hi> did evil in ſwearing by I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols: But <hi>Iacob</hi> did not evil in receiving ſuch an oath of him, though it were an vnlawful oath, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 31.53.</p>
               <p n="48">48 Though <hi>the Vſurer</hi> doth evil in ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king vſurie; yet <hi>the Borrower</hi> doth not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil in giving vſurie.</p>
               <p n="49">49 If a man may lawfully pay, for any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity, more then it is worth: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may not he, as lawfully, reſtore more then was lent him?</p>
               <p n="50">50 It is lawful <hi>to ſuffer iniury:</hi> though it be not lawful <hi>to offer iniurie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="51">51 <hi>To take vſury,</hi> is as it were <hi>to offer iniurie,</hi> and <hi>to giue vſury,</hi> is as it were <hi>to ſuffer iniurie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="52">52 Therefore, though a man may not require more then hee lent, yet may hee giue more then he borrowed.</p>
               <p n="53">53 The concluſion is this. <hi>No man muſt pay vſurie vnto Vſurers, but for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:5421:42"/>
               <p n="54">54 Even as a Traveller giveth his Purſe vnto a Theefe; becauſe he cannot chooſe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> VVhat Vſurers ſhould doe with their Gaine.</head>
            <p>THe beſt thing is <hi>to do no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g:</hi> but the next is, <hi>to make him ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The Vſurer, becauſe hee hath tranſgreſſed againſt <hi>the firſt,</hi> let him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour to fulfill <hi>the ſecond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>He that ſtole, let him ſteale no more;</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.28. But is that inough? No. What remaineth? <hi>He muſt make restitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Levit</hi> 6.2.3.4.5.6 <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p n="4">4 So, It is not inough, that the Vſurer <hi>take no more vſurie,</hi> but he muſt <hi>reſtore</hi> that which he hath taken.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:5421:43"/>
            <p n="5">5 If a man cannot ſay, as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid; <hi>VVhoſe goods haue I taken.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.3. Then muſt he ſay, as <hi>Zaccheus</hi> ſaide; <hi>VVhoſe goods haue I kept. Luke.</hi> 19.8.</p>
            <p n="6">6 As humility is the repentance of pride; and abſtinence the repentance of ſurfet; and almes the repentance of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetoſnes; and forgiuenes the repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of malice: So is reſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of vſurie.</p>
            <p n="7">7 He which is not humble, doth not repent his pride; he which doth not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine, doth not repent his gluttony; hee which doth not giue almes, doth not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his covetouſnes; he which doth not forgive, doth not repent his malice: So he which doth not reſtore, doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent his vſurie.</p>
            <p n="8">8 For how can hee be ſaide to repent his vſury, which liveth ſtil by vſurie.</p>
            <p n="9">9 As Daniel ſaid to Nabuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.24. <hi>Breake of thy ſins by righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes:</hi> So may it be ſaide to the Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:5421:43"/>
               <hi>Breake of thy vſurie by reſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 But as the Diſciples of Chriſt ſaid <hi>Ioh</hi> 6.60. <hi>This is a hard ſpeech:</hi> So ſaith the <hi>Vſurer,</hi> that hath gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al his wealth by vſurie, <hi>This is a hard ſpeech.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 Obiect. <hi>If I reſtore al I haue gotten by vſurie,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I ſhall haue nothing left to liue vpon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Anſ. Zaccheus</hi> did not feare howe he ſhould liue; but Zaccheus feared to offend.</p>
            <p n="13">13 As the Prophet ſaid to <hi>Amaziah;</hi> ſo may it be ſaid to the <hi>Vſurer; The Lord is able to giue thee more then this.</hi> 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 25 9.</p>
            <p n="14">14 Feare not to reſtore other mens goods; and trie him that ſaith. <hi>Proue me now here with, if I will not open the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto you &amp; powre you out a bleſſing without meaſure. Malach.</hi> 3.10</p>
            <p n="15">15 Queſt. <hi>VVhat if a man cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it to the right Owners, nor to their Heires.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:5421:44"/>
            <p n="16">16 <hi>Anſ.</hi> Then giue it vnto the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and to the Poore, and repent that thou haſt kept it ſo long.</p>
            <p n="17">17 Queſt. <hi>Put caſe a man bee fallen in decay, and be not able to make reſtitution as he would what then ſhall hee doe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18 <hi>Anſ.</hi> Let him acknowledge the fault, and God will accepte the wil for the deede.</p>
            <p n="19">19 For ſo Paule ſaith. 2. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 8.12 <hi>If there be a willing mind, it is accepted according to that which a man hath, and not according to that which he hath not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20 Queſt. <hi>VVhat if the VSVRER bee dead; Muſt his Heires reſtore that which was gotten by Vſurie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21 <hi>Anſw.</hi> They may<note n="*" place="margin">Note.</note> not keepe it in any caſe; for it is none of theirs.</p>
            <p n="22">22 They muſt put away the execrable thing from among them: and Goodes gotten by Vſurie, and oppreſſion, are execrable, vnto the VSVRER, and his Heires; as was the Wedge of Goulde
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:5421:44"/>that Achan ſtole. <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> 6.16. They muſt make reſtitution then.</p>
            <p n="23">23 Though it be ſweete in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet as Abner ſaide to Ioab, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.26. <hi>Knoweſt thou not that it will bee bitternes in the latter end?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24 <hi>If THEY be conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned</hi> which giue not their owne Goodes vnto them that haue neede of it: <hi>How can THEY be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> that drawe other-mens Goodes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them that haue more neede of theirs!</p>
         </div>
         <epigraph>
            <q>
               <bibl>Reuel. 7.12.</bibl>
               <p>Amen; Praiſe, and Glorie, and VViſedome, and Thankes, and Honor, and Power, and Might, <hi>be</hi> vnto OVR GOD for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more; Amen.</p>
            </q>
         </epigraph>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:5421:45"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped in the Printing</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Lin.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Fault.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Correct.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>21:</cell>
                     <cell>7:</cell>
                     <cell>the the</cell>
                     <cell>the</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>13:</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22:</cell>
                     <cell>22:</cell>
                     <cell>from</cell>
                     <cell>for</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>42:</cell>
                     <cell>9:</cell>
                     <cell>mortall</cell>
                     <cell>moral</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44: 45:</cell>
                     <cell cols="3">Theſe two pages are tranſpoſed, the latter muſt be read firſt, and the former followeth
 </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>44:</cell>
                     <cell>1:</cell>
                     <cell>he</cell>
                     <cell>they</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>2:</cell>
                     <cell>he</cell>
                     <cell>they</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>52:</cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>oar</cell>
                     <cell>our</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>54:</cell>
                     <cell>13:</cell>
                     <cell>Matth: 45</cell>
                     <cell>Matth: 5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>55:</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>is</cell>
                     <cell>in</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>12:</cell>
                     <cell>come</cell>
                     <cell>commeth</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>56:</cell>
                     <cell>16:</cell>
                     <cell>gaine</cell>
                     <cell>againe</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>57:</cell>
                     <cell cols="3">Betweene the 11: and 13: Poſitions, this muſt be added. 12. Vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that never lent vs any thing nor are able to lend <hi>For Sinners lend vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of whom they haue borroved.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5421:45"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
